let's actually do some markdown um when
the video chat starts it would be great
if you could C to the chat that's true I
asked them to help me keep the chat
relevant so we'll see um that's the hard
part about having a studio audience
right they like to have fun and they
should be able to have fun and please
make a comment if you have any comments
to make about the use of markdown please
make those oh yeah there we go Alexander
that's a great comment all right so how
do we do this all right the first thing
I need to do is get you on to github.com
there are separate videos about how and
why to use github.com I am not going to
talk about it now it it's just too much
information go to your GitHub account
and log in and once you log in we're
going to make a repository now we
already went through how to make a
repository you can have one that has
notes on there if you want to use that
same repository or we can make a new one
it's totally up to you feel free
experiment you're not going to break
anything right so I'm going to go into
my notes and I am going to look at my
notes link and you're like there's going
to be at least one person out there
that's going to be like why are we using
GitHub to take notes and learn markdown
the answer my friends is that you
haven't learned the terminal yet okay
and I want to go over markdown and
making a basic website before we get too
far along in this beginner boost so that
you can start taking advantage of using
markdown for why it was invented by a
writer to take notes and to share data
with others you can start using markdown
today there is no textbook for the
beginner boost there is your codebook
your notes and so you are the one
writing your own book you'll be able to
remember it better you'll be able to
search it better you'll know where it is
you can add stuff to it later um I don't
think I swore but okay you can use it to
your to the fullest extent the way you
want to use it so that's why we are
covering this at this time so we will
come back and we'll you'll learn how to
do it from the command line or with B
code or whatever way you want to do it
so somebody out there's like well why
are we using GitHub this is a very
inefficient way to do it it actually
isn't it's pretty nice so the first
thing I want you to see here is that
when you open up your repo um let's
actually pretend like we don't have this
let's go ahead and delete the repo in
fact let's go ahead and delete this repo
and recreate it there's really nothing
wrong with that we're going to go delete
it U I want to take you all the way
through the steps uh it says I want to
delete this repo uh and unexpected I
have red yes okay so I have to actually
type it in rvx Rob GH test one I have
just so that I whoops uh oh do I have to
use my security key all right I think I
have a security key set up let me go
check really quick I want to make sure
um yeah actually youone tabl or security
key back use this one
here where are
you um I use a I use what's called a u
key uh for security so I have to touch
it if you're going to do a thing okay so
here we go so back to main so here
here's your your empty
[Laughter]
site okay so we're going to click on new
and we're going to make a new one let's
call it
um uh there you go you could call it
whatever you want here um I mean you
could if you want to you could say
markdown tutorial right or you could
just say notes Let's do let's do notes
uh let say notes and say uh random uh
notes about stuff I'm uh learning let's
actually make it private I don't really
want people to see it there's another
video about why and when you might want
to do that um if you do it as a read me
if you add to read me to it then it
automatically makes you the readme file
uh we don't need a license so create
repository Rob deletes GitHub by
mistake so here we go random notes about
learning stuff as you can see it already
added some stuff we're going to click on
the little uh pencil icon over here and
you see you already have some stuff this
is not really well I'm going to zoom in
250% so you can see a little bit better
um but as you can see here's the name
you can change the name up here if you
want um that's also the way to add a new
file I found out uh this is not
completely obvious but um uh if you
wanted to add a new thing here it's like
you could say sample MD um and if you
say something like that you can say um
uh you know like
headers we're going to do all this give
me a second here headers here
um and and stuff and let's go ahead and
scroll down and where's my save where's
my oh commit it's commit changes which
you would never commit this often my
friends um you would never normally do
this this is if you're when we get to
GitHub this is the kind you committing
to Maine and all this stuff there's at
least one person who's going to be like
oh my God you're encouraging people to
commit to Maine all the time we're just
using this as kind of a way to save you
don't know about the incres of git yet
and you don't need to know that right
now you're just using it as a way to
save you'll notice that it actually
shows you the preview and you click on
code and you get the actual code um you
can see what you know who changed what
and when but those are all things for
later um if you want to go back and edit
the same file you can click here um if
you click on the notes directory now
you'll see we're kind of zoomed in too
much let's go back out a little bit
there we go um here you can see that
there's more than one file there's the
read me which is automatically actually
I renamed it by changing the name um and
you know you can add new files you can
add a file here you can upload a file if
you want uh you can actually upload
pictures if you take if you take a
screenshot for example example during
your during your you know whatever
you're doing here you can take a
screenshot and you can upload your
screenshot in here and we'll show you
how to do that um in fact I'm trying to
keep this video short we're going to try
to do all of basic markdown in one go um
there's not a lot you have to really
learn here and again I I'm not going to
give you a link to a book about it I'm
going to help you make your own book all
right so let's go through the sample and
let's click on this little edit the file
thing here and will go through them all
so the the first thing is head headers
so headers um if you know markdown you
know that there's many ways to do
headers um and I'm going to help you by
simplifying a few things so the thing to
keep in mind here is that you could use
uh one uh hashtag uh for for main
header um sorry heading they heading not
headers or heading I'm use the
terminology that's going to match
HTML um headings so one for a main
heading um and then uh you could do
actually let's just do this let's say uh
one for main heading and let's just make
an example of this um uh two
for uh secondary
heading um three 4 uh third
level and I'm not using H1 and H3 on
purpose you're going to see how these
translate
later um uh and then let's see you could
actually say uh I don't know how to do
this so say
four fourth
level uh but don't don't use this don't
it's not really useful it doesn't really
show up
differently uh and five
uh fifth level there's actually
six um seriously past this it there's
really very little
differentiation
um six
level
um so really the main ones you're going
to use is this and this um
um uh usually
usually it is best to keep uh the main
heading as as the
first uh line of the
document um so that it can be
easily uh parsed out of the file and I
use this all the time this is a
technique that I
use um second um
uh main uh division of content
within uh a given
document uh this is usually uh usually
best to only have a
single uh main heading per document and
this is not required but it's generally
a good idea
um and okay is it second level there
third level main division of content
within the document um uh really the
smallest um
heading uh that is
practical in most uh in most
cases um down here
um not
easily uh
distinguishable
in in by most uh by most um renderers
R
renderers uh by the
way
never never
use um
headings uh as uh for
formatting um so there's something
called
semantic uh meaning which I'll make a
video on separately let me just make a
note to make a video about that um
uh so let's talk about that let's take
I'm going to make an extra
video uh what is
semantic uh and why do I
care so I'll make a video about that but
um in a nutshell semantic is when you
use a
thing uh to distinguish meaning as
opposed to formatting and that is not
completely the definition of the word
but still um so here we go headings for
forting now we haven't been previewing
this while we're going we could just
click over here on preview and you can
see this stuff changing this is why
we're using GitHub so GitHub has got
this really
amazing um built-in previewer uh so you
can go back and forth between the
previewer and and you can
see um and and I think that that's the
way to go um
because especially if you're just
beginner right but as you can see after
the second level things kind of Trail
off right so the standard GitHub
rendering of this and by the way the
rendering the rendering of GitHub is
completely dependent on the renderer
right um I do like to use the GitHub uh
rendering as a guide somewhat for my
decisions about how this generally going
to appear in other documents um but you
know there's other places that would
render it differently so that is it's
GitHub is a pretty good you know this
this one of the main reasons I use this
preview are because you can get a good
sense of what most people think
something should look like um but the
idea of markdown is to
disconnect um the importance and the
meaning of the content you know the
different parts of content from its
appearance um so that if you're you know
if you're on a screen like this you know
you can make color distinctions where
you can't necessarily make size
distinctions in the font for example
this is one of the main advantages of
markdown is because it allows you to
provide uh a way of signaling uh to the
tool that's being used to consume the
content a way of of to say hey you need
to display this part of the content
differently depending on how it's being
displayed whether it's in a tech
terminal that where everything's the
same font size or you're you're on a big
screen or whatever right um so that's
the point so and as you can see the
first level heading the second level
heading and the third level heading uh
are really the only distinctions after
that it's like is that a header I can't
really tell it absolutely is because you
see this little link over here so GitHub
automatically makes it so that you can
click on this and you can get up here
see look at that you get an actual link
this is called a local link and it will
it will go directly to that part of your
notes yet another reason to use markdown
on GitHub for your notes is you can
refer to other areas in your notes
automatically and you can take the
immediate advantage of using the
worldwide web as God you know God being
Tim burner Lee intended um three of the
third or third level not really the
smartest fourth level fifth level sixth
level so there are no more than six
levels now it's important that I at
least mention to you if you're going to
do this that there is another way to use
headings and I'm just going to tell you
don't do it okay so so we're going to
make a little thing here uh just say
just say no to the other types of
headings um of headings and this is
actually the this is one of these times
when markdown gives you multiple ways of
doing something um so that the writer
can exercise artistic license in how
they want to write it and you really
didn't need that and this is this is we
we talked about you know HTML being
created by scientists you know there's
one specific way for something and then
you know markdown is being created by
artists and writers and so there's
usually multiple ways of doing something
and the truth is you really want the
middle of ground of that you don't want
to get into the habit of you know using
different ways to do headings because it
complicates the parsing it complicates
it's more for you to remember at the
very least um and it also can if if you
want to write your own parser which is
really fun um you know it simplifies the
parser that you'll up writing because
there's only one way to parse a heading
for example so when we talk about
simplified common Mark we're going to be
talking about that specific thing we are
going to simplify some of these
decisions and one of those decisions is
headings so there is another way to do a
heading and I'm going to just show it to
you but I am not going to put it in here
if I wanted to do this heading instead
of this this is 100% valid this is
another way to do this heading looks
kind of cool huh does right try to parse
that though
man it's really let's see if it previews
it right yep it previews it right um I
forget the name of this I don't think
it's ATX I think ATX headers are the
ones with the the hashtag just use the
hashtag um don't use that there's
there's there's two forms that are
supported uh that or the single Dash and
this this is H2 um there are some
parsers and tools out there that
explicitly forbid the use of headings
using that method so I strongly
encourage you not to do that uh and now
you know what types those are um those
you let's see I'm going to put using uh
a
or um okay so just don't use the other
ones let's preview that as you can see
we've already got a little bit of mark
down there we're going to get to that um
I got to go faster through this though
so let's go ahead and commit these
changes uh just go ahead and commit it
and now the notes about headings are
done so we've covered headings um I I
wonder if we should break down this
video and have um and have these be
different and we have different video on
each one of these what do you guys think
probably important to do that two three
four let's do that um headings um let's
do
headings uh yeah learn headings this I
don't know I I thought was going to be
like a 4 Hour
[Music]
video
so uh what do you guys think learn uh
markdown let see common Mark markdown
headings all right let's let's do that
I'm going to end the video there and and
um and um we're gonna we're going to do
the next one so